# Oliver Calder

Firmware Engineer and open source software developer, with particular emphasis on low-level systems, including kernels, storage, and virtualization. Highly skilled in C and Python with experience in Rust and a strong interest in functional languages. Uses first principles to seek efficient, modular solutions to problems. I am a full-time Linux user who supports open source software and ethical computing, and I am a clarinetist and pianist with a deep passion for classical music.

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# Firmware Engineer, Seagate Technology

JUL 2022 - PRESENT

- Wrote and debugged firmware for next-generation dual-actuator enterprise hard drives.
- Worked in C and ARM assembly, using UDS dumps and hardware emulators to identify, understand, and solve firmware problems.

# **Software Engineering Intern**, Cray/Hewlett Packard Enterprise

JUN 2021 – SEP 2021

- Built and released software and security updates for the Cray XCCS line of supercomputers.
- Wrote scripts to identify unpatched security vulnerabilities and allow the team to respond more quickly to customer needs.

# Data Research Assistant, Minnetronix, Inc.

DEC 2019 - JAN 2020

- Built automation scripts to streamline data processing workflow and scale up speed dramatically.
- Used Python to verify and manipulate spreadsheets and script file management in a Windows environment.

# Computer Science Prefect, Lab Assistant, Carleton College SEP 2019 – JUN 2022

- Communicate key Computer Science concepts to students in a way which builds on their current understanding and reinforces algorithmic problem-solving skills.
- Guide students through debugging their own code, encouraging efficient and consistent solutions to problems.

#### RESEARCH

# **Exploratory Operating Systems**, Carleton College

JUN 2020 — SEP 2020, DEC 2021

- Wrote a minimal unikernel in Rust, designed for use in serverless contexts and optimized for speed and simplicity.
- Developed performance benchmarks to compare the Rust unikernel to Linux, Docker, and processes, and demonstrated that the Rust unikernel dramatically outperformed industry standards.

## Sonic Signatures, Carleton College

JUN 2019 – JUN 2020

- Wrote modularized Python scripts to process Shakespeare plays into character phoneme data for use in machine learning classification.
- Used scikit-learn to predict characteristics of individual characters using a variety of machine learning models.
- Streamlined the process of scraping, processing, and classification, into three modular multi-threaded command-line tools.

6020 Galpin Lake Rd Excelsior, MN 55331 United States +1 952-454-6850 oliver@calder.dev

**LinkedIn**: olivercalder **GitHub**: olivercalder **Website**: calder.dev

### **EDUCATION**

# Carleton College Northfield, MN

SEP 2018 - JUN 2022

B.A. Computer Science, Mathematics | GPA: 3.85

#### RELEVANT COURSEWORK

ΑI

Advanced Algorithms
Combinatorial Theory
Computability and Complexity
Computational Mathematics
Computer Systems
Computer Graphics
Data Structures
Differential Equations
Linear and Abstract Algebra
Multivariable Calculus
Operating Systems
Probability
Programming Languages
Quantum Computing
Software Design

#### **AWARDS**

David Pollatsek '96 Prize in Computer Science Distinction in Mathematics

Graduated Cum Laude

### **LANGUAGES**

Expert: C, Python

Skilled: Bash/sh, Rust, Scheme

Familiar: Java, Go, SQL, assembly

#### **SKILLS**

AI, automation, concurrency, containerization, firmware, gdb, git, HPC, Jira, Jenkins, kernel development, LaTeX, Linux, ML, parallel computing, qemu, vim, virtualization, UDS, unikernels